<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<foo>
    <span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/thinker.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>The Thinker and Female Figurine from Cernavod?,Fired Clay,Hamangia, Cernavod?, 50004600 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span><br /><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);">National History Museum of Romania, Bucharest: 15906, 15907<br />Photo: Marius Amarie<br /></span></strong><b><br /></b>In 1956 these two figurines were found among the grave goods excavated at the Hamangia necropolis of Cernavod?. The male figure, elbows on his knees and hands on either side of his face, sits on a low four-legged stool. The woman, seated on the ground, has one leg extended forward and the other bent at the knee. In the Neolithic period, male figurines constituted a small minority of the very large corpus of figurines found both in necropoleis and in households. Even more striking is the fact that The Thinker is coupled with a female figurine, a decided rarity that clearly indicates a direct relationship between the two. While his gesture has been interpreted as reflective of a pensive state, it could also be taken as a symbol of mourning. Both figurines were deposited in a grave beside the inhumed body, as if to accompany the deceased into the afterlife.</p><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/femalefigurine2.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><b>Female Figurine,Fired Clay,Hamangia, Baïa, 50004600 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span><br /></b><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);"><strong>National History Museum of Romania, Bucharest: 11662<br />Photo: Marius Amarie</strong></span></p><p align=""><br />Hamangia refers to a group of settlements and cemeteries located in southeastern Romania and northeastern Bulgaria that date from the mid-sixth through the mid-fifth millennia <small>BC</small>. The figurines produced by these groups are marked by a lack of detail in the body parts and by the absence of heads. They are generally defined instead by pillar necks, wide hips, and arms that frequently end without hands. Many are shown with large breasts and bellies, prompting some scholars to read them as pregnant females, thus relating them to rituals of fertility and fecundity.</p><div></div><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/femalefigurine1.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Female Figurine,Fired Clay,Cucuteni, Dr?gu?eni, 40503900 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span><br /></strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);"><strong>Boto?ani County Museum, Boto?ani: 7558<br />Photo: Marius Amarie</strong></span></p><p align=""><br />Female figurines were fashioned by virtually every Neolithic cultural group, and are the most widely known category of objects from Old Europe. The miniaturized female bodies, as in this figurine, are characterized by abstraction with truncated, elongated, or emphasized body parts, and their surfaces are decorated with incised or painted geometric and abstract patterns. The heightened sense of female corporality has led traditional scholarship to identify these figurines as representations of a powerful mother goddess, whose relationship to earthly and human fertility is demonstrated by the remarkable, sexualized forms. However, this single, overarching interpretation has recently been challenged: the great variety of contexts in which the figurines are found (burials, households, hoards, and sanctuaries) suggests that they might have assumed different social, cultural, and even religious connotations according to the specific audience and environment for which they were modeled.</p><div></div><p></p><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/zoomorph.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Zoomorphic Appliqués, Possibly Representing Bulls,Gold,Varna, Varna, Grave 36, 44004200 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span><br /></strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);"><strong>Varna Regional Museum of History: 1633, 1634<br />Photo: Rumyana Kostadinova Ivanova</strong></span><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);"><strong><br /></strong></span><br />Excavated in 1974, the two appliqués formed part of a rich array of grave goods that included gold, copper, flint, bone, and ceramic objects. Possibly functioning as amulets, the two animals have been identified as bulls by the shapes of their horns and tails. Representations of bulls are widespread among Neolithic societies. Their association with divinities related to nature and agriculture, and to rituals of fecundity and fertility, is well established.</p><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/bracelet.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Spondylus Bracelet,Spondylus,Hamangia Culture, Cernavod?, ca. 50004600 bc<br /></strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);"><strong>National History Museum of Romania, Bucharest: 11666<br />Photo: Marius Amarie<br /></strong></span><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);"><strong><br /></strong></span><br />Made of Spondylus gaederopus, a shell found only in the Mediterranean Sea, this bracelet attests to the oldest long-distance trade of a specific, identifiable natural resource. Archaeological excavations throughout modern Europe have confirmed the existence in the fifth millennium <small>BC</small> of a complex exchange network that allowed for transportation of this precious material over nearly three thousand kilometers, from the Aegean coasts all the way to Britain. Traded mostly in an unworked or roughly worked state, the shells were locally carved to fulfill the desired aesthetics of the Neolithic societies that acquired them. This conically shaped bracelet is made from a single shell and is of a type favored by the Hamangia culture.</p><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/axe.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Axe,Copper,Cucuteni, Bogd?ne?ti, 37003500 bc<br /></strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);"><strong>Moldova National Museum Complex, Ia?i: 740<br />Photo: Marius Amarie</strong></span></p><p align=""><br />Copper metallurgy was a fundamental innovation that changed life not just in Old Europe, but for all European societies. The discovery of smelting permitted metalworkers to extract huge quantities of pure metallic copper from the abundant malachite and azurite ores of southeastern Europe, and led quickly to the excavation of large mines in Bulgaria and Serbia.<br />The differing styles of cast hammer-axes and axe-adzes, the most complex products of Old European metallurgy, suggest that there might have been three principal regional schools of copper metalworking: one centered in Bulgaria, another in northern Serbia, and a third somewhere in the western Carpathians. The strongly arched shape of this axe relates it to the Carpathian school of metalworking. Suggestions of wear can be found throughout its surface.</p><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/archfigure7.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Architectural Model with Seven Figurines,Fired Clay,Cucuteni, Ghel?ie?ti, 37003500 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span> <br /></strong><strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);">Neam? County Museum Complex, Piatra Neam?: 1255012552, 1320913213<br />Photo: Marius Amarie<br /><br type="_moz" /></span></strong></p><p align="">Five large female figurines and two small males were found inside this loosely rectangular architectural structure. The opening possibly indicates a doorway, while the painted geometric patterns resemble known decorations from Cucuteni households and temples, suggesting that the model represents a domestic or religious space. The miniaturization of both the human figures and the architectural structures elucidates the complex relationship between Old Europeans and the built spaces defining their communities.</p><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/archimodel.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Architectural Model,Fired Clay,Gumelni?a, C?scioarele, 46003900 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span><br /></strong><strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);">National History Museum of Romania, Bucharest: 12156<br />Photo: Marius Amarie<br /><br type="_moz" /></span></strong><b><br /></b></p><p align="">Excavated in 1966 at C?scioarelea river-island settlement of the Gumelni?a culturethis architectural model was discovered close to a large house and a sacrificial area, identified as a sanctuary and characterized by what were possibly a bench-altar and numerous cult vases. The surface of the model is enlivened by incisions and paint that define a series of four architectural buildings, variously interpreted as temples or households. Each of the buildings has an arched doorway with gables similar to a bulls horns. The buildings are set on a relatively tall substructure decorated with horizontal lines and ten round holes. This substructure may represent a stylized tell, or artificial mounds. Neolithic models are usually seen as cult objects that reflect an unknown religious custom.</p><div></div><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/glob.lg__0.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Monumental Tripartite Vessel,Fired Clay,Cucuteni, Scânteia, 42004050 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span><br /></strong><strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);">Moldova National Museum Complex, Ia?i: 17266, 19266<br />Photo: Marius Amarie</span></strong></p><p align=""><br />Found in a domestic context, this spherical vessel rests on a hollow cylindrical stand and is covered by a bell-shaped lid. The three elements were meant to be used as an ensemble and are covered with a pattern of interlocking black spiral outlines placed against a red background. While the vessels ultimate function is still subject to debate, its impressive monumental size, combined with its complex tripartite construction and intricate decoration, suggests a ceremonial purpose clearly distinct from the original utilitarian function of ceramics.</p><div></div><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/anthroVessel.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Anthropomorphic Vessel,Fired Clay,Cucuteni, Scânteia-Dealul Bode?ti, 45004050 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span><br /></strong><strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);">The Institute of Archaeology, Ia?i: 3027<br />Photo: Marius Amarie<br /></span></strong><br />Shaped in the form of a human body, this vessel has a recognizable torso and legs that are emphasized by means of grooves and white paint. Arms are suggested by the two pierced handles. The terracotta piece probably functioned as a drinking vessel.<b><br /></b></p><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/amphorae.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Amphora,Fired Clay,Cucuteni, Poduri-Dealul Ghindaru, 37003500 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span><br /></strong><strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);">Neam? County Museum Complex, Piatra Neam?: 16422<br />Photo: Marius Amarie</span></strong></p><p align=""><br />During the last phase of Cucuteni history, human figures and animalspreviously present only as three-dimensional figurines that were more or less naturalistically renderedbegan to appear also as painted decorations on ceramic vessels. This amphora, thought to be used for storage of both liquids and solids, shows two decorative registers outlined in black color over an off-white polished background. The main register is characterized by a complex arrangement of ovals, trapeziums, triangles, and diamonds, all defined by series of concentric lines. The background of the vessel contains ten highly stylized human figures comprised of two mirrored triangles surmounted by a circle to outline the body and the head, and two swerving lines terminating in disks to depict arms. Often interpreted as female figures, these forms raise interesting questions related to the supposed, but not certain, existence of a Cucuteni pantheon, and to a possible ritualistic use for the vessel.</p><div></div><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/pintadera.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Pintadera,Fired Clay,Cucuteni, Bode?ti-Frumu?ica, 44504200 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span><br /></strong><strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);">Neam? County Museum Complex, Piatra Neam?: 1227<br />Photo: Marius Amarie<br /><br /></span></strong></p><p align="">Pintaderas, or ornamental clay stamps, are a visually striking but highly enigmatic category of artifacts found during the Neolithic period at sites across Europe and Asia. Featuring a wide array of decorative motifs, including meanders, spirals, waves, and zigzag lines, the seals may have been used to print or impress onto a range of materials (textiles, leather, human skin, and even bread). Interestingly, the patterns incised on the discs find close comparisons with those painted on contemporaneous ceramic vessels and other decorated artifacts.</p><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/pinta1.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Pintadera in the Shape of a Left Leg,Fired Clay,Star?evo-Cri?, Z?uan, 6200 5500 <span style="font-size: smaller;">BC</span><br /></strong><strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);">County Museum of History and Art, Zal?u: 25/1977<br />Photo: Marius Amarie<br /><br /></span></strong></p><p align="">This pintadera in the shape of a left leg was found in a domestic context at a site belonging to the Star?evo-Cri? culture, one of the first and oldest identifiable cultural groups of Old European farmers. This pintadera is decidedly exceptional, particularly when compared with the common circular type with small knobs. The leg would have been held by the individual who was using it to mark an object with its zig-zag insignia. Whether the leg carried symbolic meaning is unknown. Its unique shape, however, suggests that it held a special place with its owner.</p><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/necklace.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Necklace (35 Shells, 26 Beads),Shell (Cardium edule, Mactra carolina),Suvorovo-Novodanilovka, Giurgiule?ti, Grave 2, 45004300 </strong><span style="font-size: smaller;"><strong>BC</strong></span><br /><strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);">The National Museum of Archaeology and History of Moldova, Chi?in?u: FB-27571-9<br />Photo: Jurie Foca and Valery Hembaruc<br /></span></strong><br />This necklace was unearthed in 1991 during excavations at the Giurgiule?ti cemetery. The burials and grave goods found there, and at forty other necropoleis spread throughout the lower Danube valley, constitute the only material remains of the Suvorovo-Novodanilovka culture, a prehistoric nomadic group. The necklace, comprised of two different shell types found in the Black Sea, was discovered in a childs grave together with other grave goods made of marble and copper.</p><span class='fadein'><img id='mainimg' style='visibility:hidden;' width='647' src='http://www.nyu.edu/isaw/exhibitions/oldeurope/sites/default/files/images/horse.lg_.jpg'></img></span>
    
    <br /><p align=""><strong>Horse-head Mace,Stone,Indo-European, Casimcea, 4000 </strong><span style="font-size: smaller;"><strong>BC</strong></span><br /><strong><span style="color: rgb(128, 128, 128);">National History Museum of Romania, Bucharest: 11650<br />Photo: Marius Amarie<br /></span></strong><b><br /></b>At the end of the fifth millennium <small>BC</small>, a series of dramatic changes took place in the lower Danube Valley. Hundreds of settlements were burned and abandoned, and the people who originally inhabited them scattered, turning to an economy based on husbandry. The sudden collapse of prominent Old European cultural groups may have been caused by a period of intense raiding by nomadic groups who came from the steppe grasslands of modern Ukraine. The graves of these nomadic people contained objects suggestive of their war-like nature, including arrows, axes, spearheads, and horse-head maces like this one,.</p>
</foo>
